Hello and welcome to the RISC OS community.
This video demonstrates the usage
of the !WakeOnLAN application
which allows you to use a RISC OS machine to
remotely start a wake-on-lan compatible computer.
One of the first things we need to know is
the network broadcast address.
Open a Task Window and then type 'ifconfig -a' to display the
network information for all interfaces attached
to this machine. Here we are interested in 'ej0'.
The broadcast address is as highlighted 192.168.1.255.
We need to remember this for later. The
MAC address is also shown under 'ether'.
It will be necessary to use a similar command on
the machine that you wish to wake to determine its MAC address.
Now let us demonstrate using the WIMP
application to remotely start another computer.
Clicking on the icon bar icon
opens the main application window.
In the top writable icon labelled 'Target MAC Addr'
enter the MAC address of the remote device.
This will need to have been determined on the
remote machine using a similar method as used
earlier for the broadcast address. Then in the
lower writable icon labelled 'IP Broadcast Addr' enter
the broadcast address we determined earlier. We are
now showing the video output of the remote device.
Clicking the 'Run' button sends the wake-on-lan
network packet to the target device and
we see the command output in the log window. As
you can see the target device is going through
its usual boot up procedure. For the purposes of
this demonstration this footage has been sped up.
Now let us demonstrate using the
command line to perform the same task.
Like most RISC OS utilities this assumes that
!WakeOnLAN has already been seen by the filer.
Open a task window and then
type the following:
'wakeonlan -m ' followed by the mac address
of the remote device which is not case sensitive
then another space followed by '-b ' and
our broadcast address in this case 192.168.1.255.
As before we are showing the
video output of the remote device.
Press ENTER and the wake-on-lan packet is sent.
Again the target device is going through its usual
sped up boot procedure. You will notice that this
command did not provide any output which can be
useful when using this command in an obey file.
We will again demonstrate using the command line
but this time include the output of the command.
As before open a task window and type 'wakeonlan -m ' followed by the mac address of
the remote device then another space followed
by '-b ' and our broadcast address and
this time add a ' -v' for verbose to
the end of the command. Press ENTER and the
wake-on-lan packet is sent. However this time
we see the output from the 'wakeonlan' command.
In this video we have shown several
ways to use the !WakeOnLAN application
to remotely start compatible machines from
your RISC OS computer.
Thanks for watching.